<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;टीका on रामायणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/kAvyam/gadyam/venkaTanAthaH/raghuvIra-gadyam/TIkA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;टीका on रामायणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/kAvyam/gadyam/venkaTanAthaH/raghuvIra-gadyam/TIkA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>shaThakopa on raghuvIra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/kAvyam/gadyam/venkaTanAthaH/raghuvIra-gadyam/TIkA/shaThakopa_on_raghuvIra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/kAvyam/gadyam/venkaTanAthaH/raghuvIra-gadyam/TIkA/shaThakopa_on_raghuvIra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org/ebook/pdf/Raghuveera%20Gadyam.pdf&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Swamy Desikan’s Raghuveera Gadyam Annotated Commentary in English by Oppiliappan KOil SrI Varadachari SaThakOpan&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;0&#34;&gt;0&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Contents Page&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Introduction to Raghuveera Gadyam 1 Commentary on Raghuveera Gadyam 8 Baala Kaandam 9 Ayodhya Kaandam 25 Kishkindha Kaandam 50 Sundara Kaandam 59 Yuddha Kaandam 61 Uththara Kaandam 102 Nigamanam 112&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;r&amp;quot;uvIr g*&amp;lt; ïIman! ve»qnawayR&amp;gt; kivtaikRk kesrI, vedaNtacayR vyaeRme siÚxÄa&amp;lt; sdaùid.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;jyTya iïts&amp;lt;Ças XvaNt ivXv&lt;snaedy&gt;, àÉavan! sItya deVya prmVyaem ÉaSkr&amp;gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;RaghuVeera Gadyam is one of the many brilliant and moving stotrams composed by Sri Vedantha Desikan, while he was residing in Thiruvahindrapuram. At this divya desam, there are the most beautiful Archa murthys of Sri Raamachandra, Sita Devi, and LakshmaNA. Swami Desikan was thrilled one day by the incomparable beauty of Sri Raamachandra giving darsanam as Kodhanda Raama at this kshetram and recollections about the extraordinary valor of our Lord and his deeds on the battlefield as the MahaVeera at Lanka. Inspired by those thoughts, he summarized in his splendid Gadyam (work in prose style) the Vaibhavam of this Maha Veera and named it appropriately Maha Veera Vaibhavam. Later this work came to be known by its popular name of Raghu Veera Gadyam.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
