<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on रामायणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on रामायणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Abandoning of sItA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/abandoning-of-sItA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/abandoning-of-sItA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: KBS Ramachandra on PrexA.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Abandoning of Sita&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of the many twists and turns in the Ramayana, the most troubling one is that of Rama abandoning Sita based on the public perception of her character.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-background&#34;&gt;The background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The difficult period of vanavasa (forest stay) was over. The trauma of losing his beloved and all the troubles to recover her from the clutches of the demon king, Ravana, were behind him. The stress of great activity and the pressures of war were all relegated to memory. His friends and allies were comfortably placed in their respective kingdoms. His brothers were with him. His mother and step mothers were peaceful without any worries. The subjects of Ayodhya had got back their beloved prince. Peace and prosperity reigned in his kingdom. He and his wife, Sita, were happy and contented. To add to all this, was the news that every Indian king (nay every person) looked forward to in great anticipation. His marriage with Sita was bearing fruit. Sita was pregnant and he was to be a father soon. This is a picture that is complete in its sense of accomplishment, satisfaction, contentment, and happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>arAdhana-instruction - shrIram</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/arAdhana-instruction_shrIram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/arAdhana-instruction_shrIram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;shrIrAm rAmAnujam&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The larger purpose of Sri Rama avatAram 1 of 5&#xA;Srimad Ramayana is regarded as sharaNAgati shastra by our AcharyAs. sharanAgati at various stages and khAnDams by many people are usually highlighted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However often overlooked is the result or the fruit of the sharanAgati. Per our AchAryas, the simple act of bhagavad ArAdhanam is the greatest gift and lesson to be learned for life in bhulokam and forever in SriVaikuntam. With the most important part of aradhanam being neivedhyam or bhojyAsanam.+++(5)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asian-rAmAyaNas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/asian-rAmAyaNas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/asian-rAmAyaNas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://threads-web.vercel.app/threads/1593263552030068736&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;#Ramayana-Hindu Culture spread throughout Asia via the Rama Story. It travelled by sea and land to China, Tibet, Turkestan, Java, Sumatra, Malaya, Burma, Thailand, Laos, Vietnam, and Cambodia. Most countries have adapted Rama Story acc. to their own culture with a local setting; the Indian names are used for important towns, sites, mountains, rivers, and lakes. The adoption of Valmiki Story in Asian countries was selective and influenced by local values.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commentaries</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/commentaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/commentaries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;These are, in roughly chronological order: the vivekatilaka of varadarAja uDAli, the rAmAnujIya attributed to rAmAnuja, the tattvadIpikA of maheSvaratIrtha, the amRtakataka of mAdhavayogin, the rAmAyaNabhUshaNa of govindarAja, the rAmAyaNatilaka of nAgeSa bhaTTa, the rAmAyaNaSiromaNi of vamSIdhara (bansidhara) SivasahAya, and the dharmAkUTam of trayambaka makhin. In addition, extracts from the commentaries of satyatIrtha, munibhAva, and sarvajnanArAyaNa have been used.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These works range in date from around the middle of the thirteenth century A. D. (in the case of varadarAja) to the eighteenth (in the case of trayambaka), and vary from the sparse glosses of the former to the dense and often copious commentaries of mAdhavayogin, govindarAja, nAgeSa, and SivasahAya, who have at least something  to say on almost every verse in the poem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Date</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/date/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/date/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/Saatvata/status/2012217331930243539&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The VR was likely composed in the span of three centuries (~5th century BC - 2nd century BC), though the broader Rāmākhyāna tradition is more archaic.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the Mahābhārata must have multiple distinct strata from 7th century BC up until the 3rd or 4th century AD.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuśa-and-lava&#34;&gt;Kuśa and Lava&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kuśa and Lava might have been invented characters whose names were back-formed from the term kuśīlava (&amp;ldquo;bard&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>devatAntara-pUjA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/devatAntara-pUjA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/devatAntara-pUjA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SVs don&amp;rsquo;t have a problem with Rama or Krishna worshipping any deity. Krishna says in Mbh that Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s head bows down only to Vishnu &amp;amp; it is taken by the Vaishnavas to mean that when He appears to be worshipping other deities, He is worshipping the antaryamin i.e. Himself. Rama has worshipped several devas in the VR and SVs don&amp;rsquo;t deny it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now coming back to rameshvara episode, the issue is different.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KhotAnese</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/khotAnese/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/khotAnese/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://unrollthread.com/t/1592060105809629185/&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Among the many regional variants of the Rāmāyaṇa, the Khotanese version is very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Maheśvara bestows on a Brāhmaṇa a jewel and a cow for all necessities of life, who then takes a wife and settles down. Many years later, the king Daśaratha, called Sahasrabāhu &amp;ldquo;the thousand-armed&amp;rdquo; here, on a hunt, carries off the wish-granting cow.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Reduced to misery, the Brāhmaṇa with his son goes around begging, until one day the son makes his way to the mountains and performs austerities. Brahmā then bestows upon him an axe, and the boy takes the name of Paraśurāma. He then slays Daśaratha/Sahasrabāhu and then goes on a rampage against the Kṣatriyas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sri D.V. Gundappa’s Essays on the Ramayana: An Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/dv-guNDappa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/dv-guNDappa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.prekshaa.in/archive?field_preksha_series_tid=7830&#34;&gt;prekshaa series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[[Sri D.V. Gundappa’s Essays on the Ramayana: An Introduction&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.prekshaa.in/article/sri-dv-gundappa%E2%80%99s-essays-ramayana-introduction&#34;&gt;prekshaa&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the first part of a new series of an English translation of D.V. Gundappa’s essays on the Ramayana written in Kannada. These essays are originally the forewords that DVG wrote for the volumes of the magnificent Kannada translation of Valmiki’s &lt;em&gt;Srimad Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;, undertaken by the late Vidwan Sri Ranganatha Sarma. They have been compiled and included in the complete works of DVG titled, &lt;em&gt;DVG Kruti Shreni&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Eminence and the Philosophy of Puranas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/vAlmIki-humor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/vAlmIki-humor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[Maharṣi Vālmīki&amp;rsquo;s sense of humour - part 1&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.prekshaa.in/maharshi-valmikis-sense-of-humour-part-1&#34;&gt;prekshaa&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;कूजन्तं राम रामेति मधुरं मधुराक्षरम् ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;आरुह्य कविता-शाखां वन्दे वाल्मीकि-कोकिलम् ॥&lt;br&gt;&#xA;[Continuously singing the sweet syllables rāma, perched upon the branch - poetry, is the cuckoo - Vālmīki, we bow down to him]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;prologue&#34;&gt;Prologue&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is well known that the author of &lt;em&gt;Śrīmad-rāmāyaṇam&lt;/em&gt; is m&lt;em&gt;aharṣi&lt;/em&gt;Vālmīki. It is known as the &lt;em&gt;ādikāvya&lt;/em&gt; i.e. the first poem. The word &lt;em&gt;ādi&lt;/em&gt; has two meanings - the first and the cause. Since it is the first poem it might have earned the epithet &lt;em&gt;ādikāvya&lt;/em&gt;. Or because it became the ideal for all the poetry which spawned subsequently it might have earned that name. All the criteria which the aestheticians prescribe for good poetry is found in this great work. All the &lt;em&gt;rasa&lt;/em&gt;s like &lt;em&gt;śṛṅgāra&lt;/em&gt; and others, all the &lt;em&gt;bhāva&lt;/em&gt;s have manifested in it. The &lt;em&gt;aṣṭādaśavarṇanā&lt;/em&gt;s (eighteen varieties of descriptions) find their place in it. Just to satisfy the criteria, the description of the forests, oceans etc, haven’t been forcefully brought in.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World of Valmiki</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/world_of_vAlmIki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/world_of_vAlmIki/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The World of Valmiki&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A compilation&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;0-introduction&#34;&gt;0 Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Valmiki’s Rāmayan is a multi layered work. The top most layer is about the physical world which he was familiar with and which he could imagine with verisimilitude. The next layer is the story of Rāma, which appeals to anyone who likes a good story. The third layer is as a work of literature, appreciated by an aesthete. The fourth layer is as a didactic work teaching moral conduct and dharma. The innermost layer is as a work of spirituality and religion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>अन्नमाचार्यः - राम-शिव-पूजायाम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/annamAchAryaH_rAma-shiva-pUjAyAm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/annamAchAryaH_rAma-shiva-pUjAyAm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://annamacharyulu.blogspot.com/2007/05/akkataa-ravanu-brahma-hatya.html?m=1&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अक्कटा रावणु ब्रह्म हत्य नीकु नेडदि&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पुक्किट पुराण लिंग पूज नीकु नेडदि&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;गुरु हत्य ब्रह्म हत्यन् गूडि द्रोणाचार्यु वंक&lt;br&gt;&#xA;हरि नी क्रुप नर्जुनुकवि लेवाय&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;यॆरवुगा गल्ललाडि येचिन धर्म राजुनकु&lt;br&gt;&#xA;परग नी यनुमतिन् पापमु लेदायनु&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अदिवो रुद्रुनि ब्रह्म हत्य बायन् गासि इच्चि&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पॊदलिन नीवतनि बूजिंतुवा&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;अदनन् पार्वतीदेवि कातंडे नी मंत्रमिच्चॆ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;वदरु माटल माया वचनालेमिटिकि&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;तगिलिन नी नाममे तारक ब्रह्ममै&lt;br&gt;&#xA;जगमु वारि पापालु संततमू बापन् गानु&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;मिगुल श्री वेंकटेश नेड मीकु पातकालु&lt;br&gt;&#xA;नगुन् बाटु लिंते काक नाना देशमुल&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ವಾಲ್ಮೀಕಿಮುನಿಗಳ ವಾಗ್ವಿಲಾಸ</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/idioms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/idioms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.prekshaa.in/archive?field_preksha_series_tid=8058&#34;&gt;prekshaa series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[[ವಾಲ್ಮೀಕಿಮುನಿಗಳ ವಾಗ್ವಿಲಾಸ&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.prekshaa.in/Valmiki-Ramayana-Idiom-Balakanda&#34;&gt;prekshaa&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;field field-name-field-body field-type-text-with-summary field-label-hidden&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;field-items&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;field-item even&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ತಮೃಷಿಂ ಮನುಷ್ಯಲೋಕಪ್ರವೇಶವಿಶ್ರಾಮಶಾಖಿನಂ ವಾಚಾಮ್&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;।&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ಸುರಲೋಕಾದವತಾರಪ್ರಾಂತರಖೇದಚ್ಛಿದಂ ವಂದೇ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;॥&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(ಅನರ್ಘರಾಘವ, ೧.೧೦)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(ಮಾತು ದೂರದ ದೇವಲೋಕದಿಂದ ಜೀವಲೋಕಕ್ಕೆ ನೀರು-ನೆರಳಿಲ್ಲದ ಕಷ್ಟದ ಹಾದಿಯಲ್ಲಿ ಹಾಯ್ದುಬರುವಾಗ ಅದಕ್ಕೆ ನೆಮ್ಮದಿಯ ವಿಶ್ರಾಂತಿವೃಕ್ಷವಾಗಿ ಪರಿಣಮಿಸಿದ ಆದಿಕವಿಗೆ ವಂದನೆಗಳು.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ರಾಮಾಯಣದ ಸ್ವಾರಸ್ಯಗಳು ನೂರಾರು; ಅವುಗಳಲ್ಲೊಂದು ನುಡಿಬೆಡಗು. ಮಾತಿನ ಈ ಪರಿಯ ಸೊಗಸಾದರೋ ಸಮಷ್ಟಿರೂಪದಲ್ಲಿ ರಸವಾಗಿ, ವ್ಯಷ್ಟಿರೂಪದಲ್ಲಿ ವಕ್ರೋಕ್ತಿಯಾಗಿ ಪರಿಣಮಿಸುತ್ತದೆ. ಇಂಥ ವಕ್ರೋಕ್ತಿಯು ವಾಕ್ಯದ ಸ್ತರದಲ್ಲಿ ಅರ್ಥಾಲಂಕಾರದ ಸೊಬಗನ್ನು ಪಡೆದರೆ, ಪದಗಳ ಮತ್ತು ವಾಕ್ಯಖಂಡಗಳ ಸ್ತರದಲ್ಲಿ ಶಬ್ದಾಲಂಕಾರದ ಹಾಗೂ ನುಡಿಗಟ್ಟುಗಳ ಚೆಲುವನ್ನು ತಳೆಯುತ್ತದೆ. ಶಬ್ದಾಲಂಕಾರಗಳನ್ನು ಬದಿಗಿರಿಸಿದರೆ ಈ ಹಂತದಲ್ಲಿ ನಮಗುಳಿಯುವುದು ನುಡಿಗಾರಿಕೆಯ ಅಂದ. ಇದು ಸಾಭಿಪ್ರಾಯವಿಶೇಷಣವಾಗಿ (ಧ್ವನಿಪೂರ್ಣವಾದ ವಿಶೇಷಣ), ವಾಚೋಯುಕ್ತಿಯಾಗಿ (ನುಡಿಗಟ್ಟು ಅಥವಾ ಇಡಿಯಮ್), ಸಾಮತಿ-ಗಾದೆಮಾತುಗಳಾಗಿ, ನಾಟುನುಡಿಯಾಗಿ ಹತ್ತಾರು ಬಗೆಯಿಂದ ವಿಸ್ತರಿಸಿಕೊಳ್ಳುತ್ತದೆ.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
