<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;भव-भूतिः on रामायणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/kAvyam/rUpakam/bhava-bhUtiH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;भव-भूतिः on रामायणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/kAvyam/rUpakam/bhava-bhUtiH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>महावीरचरितम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/kAvyam/rUpakam/bhava-bhUtiH/mahAvIracharitam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/kAvyam/rUpakam/bhava-bhUtiH/mahAvIracharitam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[महावीरचरितम्&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=MjEyMDMyNjM1NTk3MjI1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LONDON:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;lt;MISSING_FIG href=&amp;quot;../books_images/U-IMG-17239064531.jpg&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WILLIAM WATTS, CROWN COURT, TEMPLE BAR.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;то&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HORACE HAYMAN WILSON,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;WITH PROFOUND RESPECT,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;AND IN GRATEFUL ACKNOWLEDGEMENT&lt;br&gt;&#xA;OF THE LEARNING, WISDOM, AND UNWEARIED KINDNESS&lt;br&gt;&#xA;WITH WHICH FOR MANY YEARS HE HAS&lt;br&gt;&#xA;DIRECTED MY STUDIES.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADVERTISEMENT.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;MISSING_FIG href=&amp;quot;../books_images/U-IMG-17239068351.jpg&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;T&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;HIS, the first edition of the Víra Charita— a Play commonly ascribed to Bhavabhúti— is grounded upon two Devanágarí Manuscripts in the Library of the East-India House.One of them, dated Samvat 1665, is written with more thanusual care and accuracy; but it is unfortunately imperfect,and does not extend beyond the fifth act. The other, bearing the year of Vikramáditya 1857, though complete, is the hastywork of an indifferent scribe, teeming with errors of allkinds; and it was found necessary in more than one instance,in the course of the last two acts, to receive in the Text thereading of Professor Wilson&amp;rsquo;s copy, now deposited in theBodleian Library at Oxford. I have carefully comparedthese Manuscripts with each other, and collated many passages of this Play with their re-productions, both in other Dramas (as in the Uttara Ráma Charita, or in the Mahánátaka), and in rhetorical works where they are frequently quoted and commented upon. But unless the sense seemed absolutely to require the adoption of any one of the various readings thus collected, I have generally abstained from admitting them in the Text now offered to the Public,as it was my plan to adhere to the London copies, whichdiffer but little from each other, and from either of whichthe Oxford Manuscript varies but in a slight degree.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
