<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on रामायणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on रामायणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Rāmāyaṇa in numbers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2021-12-16_the-ramayaNa-in-numbers-meters-sarga-and-kaNDa-struchture/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2021-12-16_the-ramayaNa-in-numbers-meters-sarga-and-kaNDa-struchture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2021/12/16/the-ramaya%e1%b9%87a-in-numbers-meters-sarga-and-ka%e1%b9%87%e1%b8%8da-structure/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Rāmāyaṇa in numbers: meters, sarga- and kāṇḍa- structure&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;context-of-ramayana&#34;&gt;Context of rAmAyaNa&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the extant Indo-European textual corpus, only in the Hindu collection&#xA;do we find two complete early epics to complement the śruti. The Iranian&#xA;epics come from a much later age than the core Avestan corpus, and in&#xA;the Greek and Celtic cases, the śruti-equivalents have been mostly or&#xA;entirely lost. As they have come down to us, the Hindu epics postdate&#xA;much of the Vedic corpus but are still in a distinct language register&#xA;that largely predates the classical Sanskrit. Thus, the numerical study&#xA;of the epics gives us essential information regarding the evolution of&#xA;the Old Indo-Aryan language and compositional technique, with general&#xA;implications for earlier branching events within Indo-European. Contrary&#xA;to the deeply flawed mainstream white indological opinion (and its&#xA;imitators), and in line with Hindu tradition, we hold that the original&#xA;Rāmāyaṇa was composed prior to the Mahābhārata. However, it is also&#xA;clear that both epics were at some point “held” by the same expositors&#xA;and redactors, resulting in some convergences. We had &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2017/02/12/the-ramaya%e1%b9%87a-and-a-para-ramaya%e1%b9%87a-in-numbers-i-epic-as-religion/&#34;&gt;earlier presented&#xA;some key&#xA;details&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;about the structure of Rāmāyaṇa and the earliest para-Rāmāyaṇa (the&#xA;Rāmopākhyāna) via numerical analysis and pointed out how the kāṇḍa-s&#xA;show both a certain unity and divergence relating to the compositional&#xA;history of the epic. Here, we extend that analysis further and draw some&#xA;inferences regarding the above-stated issues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Rāmāyaṇa and a para-rāmāyaṇa in numbers-I: epic as religion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2017-02-12_the-ramayae1b987a-and-a-para-ramayae1b987a-in-numbers-i-epic-as-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2017-02-12_the-ramayae1b987a-and-a-para-ramayae1b987a-in-numbers-i-epic-as-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2017/02/12/the-ramaya%e1%b9%87a-and-a-para-ramaya%e1%b9%87a-in-numbers-i-epic-as-religion/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This note may be read as part of our studies on the Rāmāyaṇa and&#xA;para-Rāmāyaṇa-s of which &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2016/08/12/some-words-on-para-ramaya%e1%b9%87a-s-i/&#34;&gt;an earlier part is presented&#xA;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A study of the epic in Indo-European tradition suggests that there were&#xA;two registers of the old Indo-European religion. While today both of&#xA;them survive together with any vigor only among the Hindus, until not&#xA;too long ago these registers showed some survival even among their&#xA;Iranian cousins. From these it is apparent the first register is the&#xA;“high religion” which manifests as śrauta and smārta performance. Among&#xA;the ārya-s this further evolved into other manifestations as seen in the&#xA;tantra-s of the sectarian traditions. Nevertheless, the Vedic base&#xA;remained the model for most of these later developments. On the other&#xA;hand the lay manifestation of religion was by the medium of the epic or&#xA;itihāsa-s in India. Their religious value elsewhere in the Indo-European&#xA;world was apparent in Greece. Indeed, in the classical Greco-Roman&#xA;confluence the last attempt of reviving the religion by emperor Julian,&#xA;which was being swept away by the “Typhonic” evil of the preta-moha,&#xA;involved a focus on the religious facet of the Homeric epics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some words on “para-Rāmāyāṇa-s”-I</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2016-08-12_some-words-on-para-ramayae1b987a-s-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2016-08-12_some-words-on-para-ramayae1b987a-s-i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2016/08/12/some-words-on-para-ramaya%e1%b9%87a-s-i/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I use the hybrid Greek-Sanskrit word para-rāmāyāṇa for all rāma-kathā-s&#xA;other than that of Vālmīki. These span a great diversity of literature&#xA;going back to relatively early times in Indo-Aryan tradition. Lots of&#xA;people have said a lot of things on this matter and we are hardly going&#xA;to review any of that here. The Rāmāyaṇa itself is enigmatic in some&#xA;ways. There is no allusion to the main characters of the epic in the&#xA;Vedic corpus just like the central pāṇḍu heroes of the Mahābhārata. Yet&#xA;the late Vedic tradition belonging to the Paippalāda branch of the&#xA;Atharvaveda remembers king Hiraṇyanābha Kauśalya a descendant of&#xA;Rāmacandra Aikṣvākava. On the other side a remote dynastic predecessor&#xA;of Rāma emperor Trasadasyu is one of the greatest heroes of the ṛgveda.&#xA;Another mighty dynastic predecessor who is remembered in the ṛgveda is&#xA;emperor Bhajeratha Aikṣvākava who is known by his more widely used name&#xA;as Bhagīratha from the time of the Samaveda brāhmaṇa-s. Another great&#xA;hero and dynastic predecessor of Rāma who is remembered in the RV is&#xA;emperor Mandhātṛ. The founder of this dynastic throne Ikṣvāku appears as&#xA;a rājarṣi in the RV. However, of the later occupants of the famed&#xA;Ikṣvāku throne we know little from Vedic literature, which often talks&#xA;of the occupants of the thrones of the Kuru and the Pañcāla. This, we&#xA;suspect, reflects the dynamics of the invasions and the subsequent&#xA;conquest of the sub-continent by the Indo-Aryans warriors coming in from&#xA;their ultimate homeland in the steppes – Ikṣavāku group branched away&#xA;from the pañcajana group and moved eastwards without major participation&#xA;in the later Vedic consolidation of the śrauta ritual. However, their&#xA;hero Rāmacandra was to have a major impact of Hindu tradition from his&#xA;para-Vedic sphere.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mongolian rAmAyaNa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-13_mongolian-ramayana/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-13_mongolian-ramayana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/12/13/mongolian-ramayana/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The vaiShNava journeying beyond the hallowed Oddiyana pITha, where he&#xA;had performed the worship of vArAhI, and karNamoTini, arrived at the&#xA;oasis of Khotan. Having obtained several manuscripts of various Indic&#xA;texts in Central Asia he moved further ahead on horse to make a&#xA;rendezvous with his Mongolian guide. Having mounted a fresh horse and&#xA;penetrated deep into the steppes they arrived after a week at the remote&#xA;outposts of what was once the organizing ground of the great Oirat&#xA;emperors, Esen Taiji and Amasanji Taiji. There he found a guru in the&#xA;lineage of the mysterious brahmin wanderer Zaya paNDita who had visited&#xA;the courts of the Chingizid Kha’khans like Mangku and Kublai, journeying&#xA;from Bihar to Tibet to Mongolia. On being introduced to the vaiShNava he&#xA;invited with respect and showed him an aged manuscripts in the Oirat&#xA;script. They were said to be translations and transcriptions of works&#xA;with Zaya paNDita. Two of them contained the tale of rAmachandra. One of&#xA;them was the ikShvAku vaMsha giving the history of the ikShvAku kings&#xA;from manu down to the nAstIka siddhArtha, and his sAkhya branch of&#xA;ikShvAkus of kapilavastu. In this the tale of rAmachandra was&#xA;considerably developed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ariesta feature</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/ariesta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/ariesta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: TW&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indo-European epic tradition has a narrative feature that is given a specific name in the Greek branch -aristeia &amp;ndash; the exaltation of a specific hero in battle. The aristeias are marked by that hero standing out in great acts of valor, often accompanied by an uncontrollable fury, with the rest almost becoming mere spectators. It has been widely noted in yavana Illiad where heroes like Diomedes, Patroclus, Hector &amp;amp; Achilleus have their aristeias which sometimes end in their death. In essence it is the highpoint of the career of the warrior.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ashvamedha niyoga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/ashvamedha-niyoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/ashvamedha-niyoga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;See it would need a long explanation to bring all the meta-points which I am not feeling inclined to now — it is something one could write a whole essay about but hardly my priority of things to write. but key points are it is clear from bAlakANDa&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1st: tasya ca evam prabhAvasya dharmaj~nasya mahaatmanaH |&lt;br&gt;&#xA;sutArtham tapya mAnasya na asiit vaMshakaraH sutaH ||&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He is clearly having a burning for the son who will extend the line — an anxiety. He has 3 wives but has not procreated. This is clearly a sign of a problem. Old tradition allows in these circumstances for an appointee with virtue to play the role of the sperm donor&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AyodhyA-lankAdi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/ayodhyA-lankAdi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/ayodhyA-lankAdi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/1743124565281096051&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ayodhya-importance&#34;&gt;Ayodhya importance&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I know saying things on a fraught topic like this will evoke ire among H but cannot resist: For us, the aikShvAkava-prAsAda has more political significance than a religious one. We acknowledge that for some people it is shuddha-brahma-parAtpara-rAma. That is not the case for us.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The rAmayaNa is a religious text as an illustration of how the pantheon headed by shatakratu filters into the ideals of the human realm as presented by vAlmIki.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Layers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/layers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/layers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oocities.org/somasushma/ram.html&#34;&gt;OO&lt;/a&gt; with addenda&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;विश्वास-टिप्पनी&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The below comments by mAnasatarangiNIkAra throw light on the connection between niyoga and ashvamedha – with particular reference to the birth of rAma. Also note ancillary remarks about how the epics can be interpreted as mirrors of the shruti; and how besides that, they must be read at many levels. And note the (very credible) theory that the current rAmAyaNa is a vaiShNava recasting of an aindra epic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Succession</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/succession/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/succession/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/blog_supplement/with_replies&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the rAmayaNa, there are 4 pairings of takeover of the throne of the elder brother by the younger:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;bharata -&amp;gt; rAma. Here, bharata ultimately turns down the throne only rules as a viceroy. This is evidently implied by vAlmIki to be the ideal that is to be contrasted with the rest.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;rAvaNa -&amp;gt; kubera&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;sugrIva -&amp;gt; vAlin&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;vibhIShaNa -&amp;gt; rAvaNa&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We believe that there is some encoded message in these iterations of the motif; however, we have not entirely cracked it.&#xA;We believe vAlmIki is presenting various grades of the situation: bharata-rAma: ideal; rAvaNa-kubera deprecated; vibhIShaNa-rAvaNa: just; sugrIva-vAlin: ambivalent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V1 frequencies</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/v1-frequencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/rAmAyaNam/meta/articles/MT_lekhAH/v1-frequencies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Frequency of mention of some common v1 clans (Baroda = &amp;ldquo;critical&amp;rdquo; edition)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Clan&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Number&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bhArgava&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bhR^igu&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;bharadvAja&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;55&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;gotama&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;kashyapa&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;kaushika&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;vasiShTha&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;133&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;vishvAmitra&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;148&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;vishvAmitra&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;186&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
